Hi.
مرحبا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I did that for two reasons.
لقد قمت بذلك لسببين.
First of all, I wanted to give you
أولا، أريد أن أعطيكم
a good visual first impression.
انطباعا مرئيا أوليا جيدا.
But the main reason I did it is that
لكن السبب الرئيسي لقيامي بذلك
that's what happens to me when I'm forced to wear
ذلك ما يحدث لي حين أكون مرغما على ارتداء
a Lady Gaga skanky mic.
ميكروفون متأرجح كذلك الخاص بالمطربة ليدي جاجا .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm used to a stationary mic.
أنا متعود على ميكروفون ثابت.
It's the sensible shoe of public address.
إنه كالحذاء الحساس الذي تلبسه أثناء الحديث أمام الجمهور
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But you clamp this thing on my head, and something happens.
لكن حين أشبك هذا الشيء على رأسي، يحصل شيء ما.
I just become skanky.
أصبح دنيئا.
(Laughter) So I'm sorry about that.
(ضحك) وبالتالي أنا آسف بهذا الخصوص.
And I'm already off-message.
وها قد خرجت عن سياق الموضوع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ladies and gentlemen,
أيها السيدات والسادة،
I have devoted the past 25 years of my life
لقد كرست ال25 سنة الماضية من حياتي
to designing books.
لتصميم الكتب.
("Yes, BOOKS. You know, the bound volumes with ink on paper.
"نعم، الكتب. تعرفون، المجلدات المنضمة ذات الحبر والورق.
You cannot turn them off with a switch.
لا يمكنك إيقاف تشغيلها بزر.
Tell your kids.")
أخبر أطفالك ".
It all sort of started as a benign mistake,
قد بدأ كل شيء نوعا ما كغلطة حميدة،
like penicillin. (Laughter)
مثل البنسلين. (ضحك)
What I really wanted
ما كنت أريده حقا
was to be a graphic designer
هو أن أصير مصمم رسوم
at one of the big design firms in New York City.
وفي واحدة من شركات التصميم الكبرى في مدينة نيويورك.
But upon arrival there,
لكن لدى وصولي إلى هناك،
in the fall of 1986, and doing a lot of interviews,
في خريف عام 1986، وبعد إجراء الكثير من المقابلات،
I found that the only thing I was offered
وجدت أن الشيء الوحيد الذي تم عرضه علي
was to be Assistant to the Art Director at Alfred A. Knopf,
هو أن أكون مساعدا لمدير الفن في نوف ألف الفريد،
a book publisher.
وهو ناشر كتب.
Now I was stupid,
الآن لقد كنت غبيا،
but not so stupid that I turned it down.
لكنني لم أكن غبيا لدرجة رفضها.
I had absolutely no idea
لم تكن لدي أدنى فكرة
what I was about to become part of,
عما كنت على وشك أن أصبح جزء منه،
and I was incredibly lucky.
وكنت محظوظاً بشكل لا يصدق.
Soon, it had occurred to me what my job was.
وقريبا، فقد اتضح لي ما كانت عليه وظيفتي.
My job was to ask this question:
وقد كانت وظيفتي طرح هذا السؤال:
"What do the stories look like?"
"ما الذي تبدو عليه القصص؟"
Because that is what Knopf is.
لأن تلك ماهية دار نوف.
It is the story factory, one of the very best in the world.
إنه مصنع قصص، أحد أفضلها في العالم.
We bring stories to the public.
نجلب القصص للجمهور.
The stories can be anything,
القصص يمكن أن تكون أي شيء،
and some of them are actually true.
وبعضها في الواقع حقيقية.
But they all have one thing in common:
ولكن لديها جميعا أمر مشترك:
They all need to look like something.
جميعا تحتاج أن تبدو مثل شيء ما.
They all need a face.
كلها تحتاج إلى وجه.
Why? To give you a first impression
لماذا؟ لتعطيكم انطباعا أوليا
of what you are about to get into.
لما أنتم على وشك الولوج إليه.
A book designer gives form to content,
يعطي مصمم الكتب شكلا للمحتوى،
but also
ولكنه أيضا
manages a very careful balance between the two.
يدير توازنا دقيقا بين الاثنين.
Now, the first day
الآن، في اليوم الأول
of my graphic design training at Penn State University,
من تدريبي في مجال تصميم الرسوم في جامعة ولاية بنسلفانيا،
the teacher, Lanny Sommese, came into the room
المدرس، لاني سميث، جاء للغرفة
and he drew a picture of an apple on the blackboard,
ورسم صورة تفاحة على السبورة،
and wrote the word "Apple" underneath,
وكتب كلمة "أبل" تحتها،
and he said, "OK. Lesson one. Listen up."
وقال، "حسنا. الدرس الأول. استمعوا".
And he covered up the picture and he said,
فغطى الصورة وقال،
"You either say this," and then he covered up the word,
"إما أن تقول هذا"، ثم غطى الكلمة،
"or you show this.
"أو تظهر هذا.
But you don't do this."
ولكن لا تقوم بالأمرين سوية. "
Because this is treating your audience like a moron.
لأن هذا يعني أنك تخاطب جمهورك كأغبياء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And they deserve better.
وهم يستحقون معاملة أفضل.
And lo and behold, soon enough,
والمثير للعجب، أنه سرعان
I was able to put this theory to the test
ما أخضعت هذه النظرية للتجربة
on two books that I was working on for Knopf.
على اثنين من الكتب التي كنت أعمل عليها في نوف.
The first was Katharine Hepburn's memoirs,
وقد كان الأول مذكرات كاثرين هيبورن،
and the second was a biography of Marlene Dietrich.
والثاني كان السيرة الذاتية لمارلين ديتريش.
Now the Hepburn book
الآن كتاب هيبورن
was written in a very conversational style,
قد كتب بأسلوب حواري جدا،
it was like she was sitting across a table telling it all to you.
وكأنها كانت جالسة على طاولة تخبركم بكل هذا.
The Dietrich book was an observation
وكتاب ديتريش كان تأملا
by her daughter; it was a biography.
من طرف ابنتها؛ لقد كان سيرة ذاتية.
So the Hepburn story is words
وبالتالي فقصة هيبورن عبارة عن كلمات
and the Dietrich story is pictures, and so we did this.
وقصة ديتريش عبارة عن صور، وبالتالي قمنا بهذا.
So there you are.
ها هي ذي.
Pure content and pure form, side by side.
محتوى وشكل نقي، جنبا إلى جنب.
No fighting, ladies.
لا داعي للقتال أيتها السيدات.
("What's a Jurassic Park?")
"ما هو منتزه جوراسي؟"
Now, what is the story here?
والآن، ما هي القصة هنا؟
Someone
شخص ما
is re-engineering dinosaurs
قام بإعادة هندسة الديناصورات
by extracting their DNA
باستخراج حمضها النووي
from prehistoric amber.
من عنبر عصور ما قبل التاريخ.
Genius!
أمر عبقري!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, luckily for me,
الآن، ومن حسن الحظ بالنسبة لي،
I live and work in New York City,
أعيش، وأعمل في مدينة نيويورك،
where there are plenty of dinosaurs.
حيث هناك الكثير من الديناصورات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So,
وهكذا،
I went to the Museum of Natural History,
فقد ذهبت إلى متحف التاريخ الطبيعي،
and I checked out the bones, and I went to the gift shop,
وفحصت العظام، وذهبت إلى محل بيع الهدايا،
and I bought a book.
واشتريت كتابا.
And I was particularly taken with this page of the book,
وقد أسرتني صفحة بعينها من الكتاب،
and more specifically the lower right-hand corner.
وتحديدا في الزاوية اليمنى في الأسفل.
Now I took this diagram,
الآن أخذت هذا الرسم التخطيطي،
and I put it in a Photostat machine,
ووضعه في آلة نسخ،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and I took a piece of tracing paper,
وأخذت قطعة من الورق الشفاف،
and I taped it over the Photostat
وألصقتها على جهاز تصوير الوثائق
with a piece of Scotch tape -- stop me if I'm going too fast --
بقطعة من الشريط اللاصق -- أوقفوني إن كنت سريعا جدا --
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
and then I took a Rapidograph pen --
وبعد ذلك تناولت قلم رابيدوغراف --
explain it to the youngsters --
اشرحوا ذلك للصغار --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and I just started to reconstitute the dinosaur.
وبدأت في إعادة تشكل الديناصور.
I had no idea what I was doing,
لم تكن لدي أدنى فكرة عما كنت أفعله،
I had no idea where I was going,
لم تكن لدي أدنى فكرة إلى أين كنت متجها بهذا،
but at some point, I stopped --
ولكنني توقفت في نقطة ما --
when to keep going would seem like I was going too far.
حين كان الاستمرار سيبدو وكأنني أبالغ.
And what I ended up with was a graphic representation
وما انتهيت إليه كان هذا الرسم التمثيلي الخاص بنا
of us seeing this animal coming into being.
ونحن نرى هذا الحيوان يظهر إلى الوجود.
We're in the middle of the process.
نحن في منتصف العملية.
And then I just threw some typography on it.
ثم قمت فقط بوضع بعض المواد الطباعية فيه.
Very basic stuff,
أمور أساسية جدا،
slightly suggestive of public park signage.
توحي شيء ما بإشارات الحدائق العامة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Everybody in house loved it,
الجميع هناك أحبها،
and so off it goes to the author.
وبالتالي أرسلناها إلى الكاتب.
And even back then,
وحتى آنذاك،
Michael was on the cutting edge.
كان مايكل في الطليعة.
("Michael Crichton responds by fax:")
"رد مايكل عبر الفاكس:"
("Wow! Fucking Fantastic Jacket")
"واو! غلاف رائع للغاية"
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
That was a relief to see that pour out of the machine.
وقد كانت رؤية ذلك يخرج من الآلة أمراً مثيرا للارتياح.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I miss Michael.
أشتاق لمايكل.
And sure enough, somebody from MCA Universal
والمؤكد أن أحدهم من ام اس ايه العالمية
calls our legal department to see if they can
اتصل بقسمنا القانوني ليروا إن أمكنهم
maybe look into buying the rights to the image,
ربما التفكير في شراء حقوق ملكية الصورة،
just in case they might want to use it.
فقط في حالة كانوا يرغبون في استخدامها.
Well, they used it.
حسنا، لقد استخدموها.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
And I was thrilled.
وقد كنت مسرورا للغاية.
We all know it was an amazing movie,
جميعنا نعرف أنه فيلم رائع،
and it was so interesting to see it
وقد كان من المثير جدا رؤيته
go out into the culture and become this phenomenon
يخرج للثقافة ويصبح ظاهرة
and to see all the different permutations of it.
ورؤية كل تبديلاته المختلفة.
But not too long ago,
ولكن منذ فترة ليست بالطويلة،
I came upon this on the Web.
وجدت هذا فجأة على شبكة الإنترنت.
No, that is not me.
لا، هذا ليس أنا.
But whoever it is,
ولكن أيا كان،
I can't help but thinking they woke up one day like,
لا أستطيع سوى التفكير أنه في أحد الأيام استيقظ وفكر،
"Oh my God, that wasn't there last night. Ooooohh!
"أوه يا إلهي، ذاك لم يكن هناك الليلة الماضية. أوووووه!
I was so wasted."
كنت فاقدا للوعي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But if you think about it, from my head
ولكن إن فكرتم في ذلك، من رأسي
to my hands to his leg.
إلى يدي ثم إلى ساقه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's a responsibility.
تلك مسؤولية.
And it's a responsibility that I don't take lightly.
وهي مسؤولية لا أستهين بها.
The book designer's responsibility is threefold:
مسؤولية مصمم كتاب لها أبعاد ثلاثة:
to the reader, to the publisher and, most of all, to the author.
للقارئ، والناشر، والأهم من ذلك كله للكاتب.
I want you to look at the author's book
أريدكم أن تنظروا إلى كتاب المؤلف
and say, "Wow! I need to read that."
وتقولوا، "واو! علي قراءة ذلك."
David Sedaris is one of my favorite writers,
ديفيد سيداريس هو أحد الكتاب المفضلين لدي،
and the title essay
والمقالة الأساسية
in this collection is about his trip to a nudist colony.
في هذه المجموعة هي حول رحلته إلى مملكة عراة.
And the reason he went is because
وسبب ذهابه إلى هناك هو أنه
he had a fear of his body image,
كان لديه خوف من صورة جسده،
and he wanted to explore what was underlying that.
وأراد استكشاف ما وراء ذلك.
For me, it was simply an excuse to design a book
بالنسبة لي، كان مجرد ذريعة لتصميم كتاب
that you could literally take the pants off of.
يمكنك حرفيا أن تنزع عنه السروال.
But when you do,
ولكن عندما تفعل ذلك،
you don't get what you expect.
لا تحصل على ما تتوقعه.
You get something that goes much deeper than that.
تحصل على شيء يذهب أعمق من ذلك بكثير.
And David especially loved this design
وقد أحب ديفيد هذا التصميم على وجه الخصوص
because at book signings, which he does a lot of,
بسبب توقيعات الكتب، وهو يقوم بالكثير منها،
he could take a magic marker and do this.
يمكنه أن يتناول قلما سحريا ويقوم بهذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Hello!
مرحبا!
Augusten Burroughs wrote a memoir
أوغستين بوروز كتب مذكرات
called ["Dry"], and it's about his time in rehab.
تدعى ["جافة"] وتتحدث عن الوقت الذي قضاه في إعادة التأهيل.
In his 20s, he was a hotshot ad executive,
في العشرينات من عمره، وقد كان أحد أفضل رجال الإعلانات التنفيذيين.
and as Mad Men has told us, a raging alcoholic.
وكما أخبرتنا قصة رجال غاضبون، أنه مدمن كحول مسعور.
He did not think so, however,
هو لم يعتقد ذلك، لكن مع ذلك،
but his coworkers did an intervention and they said,
لكن زملاءه في العمل تدخلوا وقالوا،
"You are going to rehab, or you will be fired and you will die."
"إما أن تذهب إلى إعادة التأهيل أو يتم طردك وستموت."
Now to me, this was always going to be a typographic solution,
الآن بالنسبة لي، كان هذا ليكون دائما حلا طباعيا،
what I would call the opposite of Type 101.
ما يمكن أن أسميه عكس نوع 101.
What does that mean?
ما الذي يعنيه ذلك؟
Usually on the first day of Introduction to Typography,
عادة في اليوم الأول من مقدمة للطباعة،
you get the assignment of, select a word
يعطى لك تكليف، حدد كلمة
and make it look like what it says it is. So that's Type 101, right?
وجعلها تبدو مثل معناها. هذا هو نوع 101، صحيح؟
Very simple stuff.
أشياء بسيطة جداً.
This is going to be the opposite of that.
وهذا سيكون عكس ذلك.
I want this book to look like it's lying to you,
أريد هذا الكتاب أن يبدو وكأنه يكذب عليكم،
desperately and hopelessly, the way an alcoholic would.
بطريق يائسة ومستميتة، بنفس أسلوب مدمن كحول.
The answer was the most low-tech thing you can imagine.
وقد كان الجواب أقل مستوى تقنية يمكنكم تخيله.
I set up the type, I printed it out on an Epson printer
قمت بإعداد النوع، وطبعته على طابعة Epson
with water-soluble ink, taped it to the wall
بالحبر المذاب في الماء، ثم لصقة على الحائط
and threw a bucket of water at it. Presto!
وألقى دلو من الماء عليها. بسرعة!
Then when we went to press,
ثم عندما ذهبنا للطباعة،
the printer put a spot gloss on the ink
وضعت الطابعة لمعانا موضعيا على الحبر
and it really looked like it was running.
ويبدو حقا وكأنه يسيل.
Not long after it came out, Augusten was waylaid in an airport
وبعد فترة ليس بالطويلة من صدوره، تم إيقاف أوغستين في المطار
and he was hiding out in the bookstore
وقد كان مختبئاً في محل بيع الكتب
spying on who was buying his books.
يتجسس على الذين يشترون كتبه.
And this woman came up to it,
فجاءت إليه سيدة،
and she squinted, and she took it to the register,
وحدقت فيه بعينين نصف مغمضتين ثم أخذته إلى السجل،
and she said to the man behind the counter, "This one's ruined."
وقالت للرجل الذي وراء الشباك، "هذا الكتاب مخرب."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the guy behind the counter said, "I know, lady. They all came in that way."
وقال الرجل وراء الشباك، "أعرف يا سيدتي. كلها جاءت هكذا."
Now, that's a good printing job.
الآن، تلك مهمة طباعة جيدة.
A book cover
غلاف كتاب
is a distillation.
هو تقطير.
It is a haiku,
إنها هايكو،
if you will, of the story.
القصة، إن صح التعبير.
This particular story
هذه القصة بعينها
by Osama Tezuka
من طرف أسامة تيزوكا
is his epic life of the Buddha,
تحكي الحياة الملحمية للبوذا،
and it's eight volumes in all. But the best thing is
وهي مكونة من ثمان مجلدات. لكن أفضل شيء هو
when it's on your shelf, you get a shelf life
عندما تكون على رفك، يكون لديك حياة رفية
of the Buddha, moving from one age to the next.
للبوذا وهو ينتقل من عمر لآخر.
All of these solutions
كل هذه الحلول
derive their origins from the text of the book,
تستمد جذورها من نص الكتاب،
but once the book designer has read the text,
ولكن بمجرد أن قرأ مصمم الكتاب النص،
then he has to be an interpreter
ومن ثم كان عليه أن يكون مفسرا
and a translator.
ومترجما.
This story was a real puzzle.
هذه الصورة كانت لغزا حقيقيا.
This is what it's about.
وهذا ما هي عليه.
("Intrigue and murder among 16th century Ottoman court painters.")
"الدسيسة والقتل بين رسامي المحكمة العثمانية في القرن السادس عشر".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All right, so I got a collection of the paintings together
حسنا، قد وضعت مجموعة من اللوحات معا
and I looked at them and I deconstructed them
ونظرت إليها ثم فككتها
and I put them back together.
ثم أعدتها معا مجددا.
And so, here's the design, right?
وهكذا، ها هو التصميم، صحيح؟
And so here's the front and the spine, and it's flat.
وبالتالي ها هي المقدمة والعمود الفقري وهي مسطحة.
But the real story starts when you wrap it around a book and put it on the shelf.
ولكن القصة الحقيقية تبدأ عندما تلفها حول كتاب ووضعه على الرف.
Ahh! We come upon them,
آه! يظهر هذا،
the clandestine lovers. Let's draw them out.
عشاق السرية. دعونا نجذبهم.
Huhh! They've been discovered by the sultan.
هه! لقد تم اكتشافهم من طرف السلطان.
He will not be pleased.
لن يتم إرضاؤه.
Huhh! And now the sultan is in danger.
هه! والآن السلطان في خطر.
And now, we have to open it up
والآن علينا أن نفتحه
to find out what's going to happen next.
لمعرفة ما سوف يحدث بعد ذلك.
Try experiencing that on a Kindle.
حاول اختبار ذلك على كيندل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Don't get me started.
لا تجعلوني أبدأ.
Seriously.
بجدية.
Much is to be gained by eBooks:
هناك الكثير مما يمكن الحصول عليه من خلال الكتب الإلكترونية:
ease, convenience, portability.
السهولة والراحة، والاحتمالات الشاسعة.
But something is definitely lost: tradition,
ولكن شيء ما قد فقد بالتأكيد: التقاليد
a sensual experience, the comfort of thingy-ness --
والتجربة الحسية والرفاهية المادية --
a little bit of humanity.
قليل من الإنسانية.
Do you know what John Updike used to do
هل تعرفون ما كان جون ابدايك يقوم به
the first thing when he would get a copy
أول شيء يقوم به حين يحصل على نسخة
of one of his new books from Alfred A. Knopf?
من أحد كتبه الجديدة من ألفريد أ. نوف؟
He'd smell it.
فيقوم بشمه.
Then he'd run his hand over the rag paper,
ثم يمرر يده على القطع الورقية،
and the pungent ink and the deckled edges of the pages.
والحبر اللاذع وحواف الصفحات الحادة.
All those years, all those books, he never got tired of it.
كل تلك السنوات، كل تلك الكتب، لم يسأم قط من ذلك.
Now, I am all for the iPad,
الآن، أميل كلية للآيباد،
but trust me -- smelling it will get you nowhere.
ولكن ثقوا بي -- اشتمامه لن يفضي إلى شيء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now the Apple guys are texting,
رجال الآبل الآن يراسلون بعضهم،
"Develop odor emission plug-in."
"طوروا مكونات إضافية تصدر روائح."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the last story I'm going to talk about is quite a story.
وآخر قصة سأتحدث عنها هي قصة فريدة.
A woman
امرأة
named Aomame in 1984 Japan finds herself
تدعى أومامي في اليابان سنة 1984 تجد نفسها
negotiating down a spiral staircase
تعبر سلما حلزوني نزولا
off an elevated highway. When she gets to the bottom,
خارج طريق سريع مرتفع. حين تصل إلى الأسفل،
she can't help but feel that, all of a sudden,
ولا يسعها إلا أن تحس أنه، فجأة،
she's entered a new reality
قد دخلت واقعا جديداً
that's just slightly different from the one that she left,
مختلف قليلا عن الذي غادرته،
but very similar, but different.
لكن مشابه جداً، ولكن مختلف.
And so, we're talking about parallel planes of existence,
ولذا، فإننا نتحدث عن مستويات تواجد متوازية،
sort of like a book jacket and the book that it covers.
نوعا ما مثل غلاف كتاب والكتاب الذي يغلفه.
So how do we show this?
لذا كيف يمكننا إظهار هذا؟
We go back to Hepburn and Dietrich, but now we merge them.
نعود إلى هيبورن وديتريش، لكن الآن علينا دمجهما معا.
So we're talking about different planes, different pieces of paper.
وبالتالي نحن نتحدث عن مستويات مختلفة، قطع ورق مختلفة.
So this is on a semi-transparent piece of velum.
ولهذا فإن هذا تم على قطعة غشاء شبه شفافة.
It's one part of the form and content.
إنه أحد أجزاء الشكل والمحتوى.
When it's on top of the paper board,
حين يكون فوق لوح الورق،
which is the opposite, it forms this.
والذي هو العكس، يشكل هذا.
So even if you don't know anything about this book,
وبالتالي حتى إذا كنت لا تعرف أي شيء عن هذا الكتاب،
you are forced to consider a single person
ستضطر إلى اعتبار شخص واحد
straddling two planes of existence.
يتداخل في مستويي وجود.
And the object itself invited exploration
والشكل في حد ذاته يدعو للإستكشاف
interaction, consideration
والتفاعل والاعتبار
and touch.
واللمس.
This debuted at number two
وهذا قد ظهر لأول مرة في المرتبة الثانية
on the New York Times Best Seller list.
على قائمة نيويورك تايمز للأكثر مبيعا.
This is unheard of,
وهذا أمر لم يسمع به من قبل،
both for us the publisher, and the author.
وكلانا الناشر والكاتب.
We're talking a 900-page book
نحن نتحدث عن كتاب من 900 صفحة
that is as weird as it is compelling,
هو غريب بقدر ما هو قهري،
and featuring a climactic scene
ويعرض مشهدا مناخيا
in which a horde of tiny people
يبرز فيه حشد من الأشخاص الصغار
emerge from the mouth of a sleeping girl
من فم فتاة نائمة
and cause a German Shepherd to explode.
ويسبب في انفجار راع ألماني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not exactly Jackie Collins.
ليس بالضبط جاكي كولينز.
Fourteen weeks on the Best Seller list,
أربعة عشر أسبوعا على قائمة الأكثر مبيعا،
eight printings, and still going strong.
ثمان طبعات، ولا تزال مستمرة بقوة.
So even though we love publishing as an art,
وبالتالي على الرغم من أننا نحب النشر كفن،
we very much know it's a business too,
نعلم تماما أنه كذلك مجال عمل،
and that if we do our jobs right and get a little lucky,
وأنه إن أدينا وظائفنا كما يجب ومع قليل من الحظ،
that great art can be great business.
يمكن أن يكون الفن تجارة مربحة.
So that's my story. To be continued.
وبالتالي تلك قصتي. على أن تستمر.
What does it look like?
ما الذي تبدو عليه؟
Yes. It can, it does and it will,
نعم. يمكنها، وهي تفعل وستفعل،
but for this book designer,
لكن بالنسبة لمصمم الكتب هذا،
page-turner,
مقلب الصفحات،
dog-eared place-holder,
معلم صفحات على شكل أذن كلب،
notes in the margins-taker,
الملاحظات على الهوامش،
ink-sniffer,
متشمم الحبر،
the story looks like this.
تبدو القصة هكذا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)